<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise containing the aequity of an humble supplication which is to be exhibited vnto hir gracious Maiesty and this high Court of Parliament in the behalfe of the countrey of Wales, that some order may be taken for the preaching of the Gospell among those people Wherein also is set downe as much of the estate of our people as without offence could be made known, to the end that our case (if it please God) my be pitied by them who are not of this assembly, and so they also may bee driuen to labour on our behalfe.</title>
            <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19611</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114395</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849620</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849620</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14779</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14779)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 516:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise containing the aequity of an humble supplication which is to be exhibited vnto hir gracious Maiesty and this high Court of Parliament in the behalfe of the countrey of Wales, that some order may be taken for the preaching of the Gospell among those people Wherein also is set downe as much of the estate of our people as without offence could be made known, to the end that our case (if it please God) my be pitied by them who are not of this assembly, and so they also may bee driuen to labour on our behalfe.</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, and are to be sold [by T. Cooke] in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Tygers head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1587.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Penry.</note>
                  <note>Bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wales --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14779:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14779:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE CONTAINING THE AEQVITY OF AN HVMBLE SVPPLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CATION WHICH IS TO BE <hi>EXHIBITED VNTO HIR</hi> GRACIOVS MAIESTY AND this high Court of Parliament <hi>in the behalfe of the Countrey of</hi> Wales, that ſome order may <hi>be taken for the preaching of</hi> the Goſpell among thoſe people.</p>
            <p>Wherein alſo is ſet downe as much of the eſtate of our people as without offence could be made known, to the end that our caſe (if it pleaſe God) may be piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them who are not of this aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and ſo they alſo may bee driuen to labour on our behalfe.</p>
            <p>AT OXFORD, Printed by IOSEPH BARNES, and are <hi>to be ſold in Pauls Church-yard at the ſigne of the Tygers head.</hi> 1587.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:14779:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14779:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>TO AL THAT MOVRN IN SION VNTIL THEY SEE Ieruſalem in perfect beuty, &amp; namely to my Fathers &amp; <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Church of England,</hi> grace, mercy and loue in the <hi>Lord Ieſus bee</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath beene the iuſt complaint (beloued in the Lord) of the godlie in all ages, that Gods eternall and bleſſed verity, vnto whom the very Heauens themſelues ſhoulde ſtoupe and giue obeſiance, hath bin of that ſmal reckoning and account in the eies of the moſt part of great men, as they valued it to be but a meere loſſe of time to yeeld anie attendaunce there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon. Hence it commeth to paſſe that the truth being at any time to be countenanced, none very often are found in the traine thereof, but the moſt contemptible and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe of men. And becauſe theſe alſo being guilty vnto themſelues of great infirmities (and foule ſinnes manie times) and not ignorant that affliction is the ſequele of earnest and ſincere profeſſion doe pull their neckes from the yoke, and their ſhoulders from the burden: the Lorde is conſtrained verie ſeuerely to deale with them before they can be gotten to go on his meſſage. Whereupon alſo followeth their endeuours in Gods owne cauſe not to haue the euents which they expect. Example hereof Ionas may be one for all. And which is farre more lamentable, in as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14779:3"/>much as the drouſie and careleſſe ſecurity, the colde and froſſen affections of the godly themſelues in most waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affaires is neuer wanting, their careful diligence, and earneſt zeale ioined with hartie, and vehement praiers alwaies deſired, the Lord ſuffereth his owne cauſe, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract ſome ſpot from their ſinful hands. Theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions beloued, but ſpecially the later, kept me back a great while from this action, which I haue now by the goodnes of God brought to this paſſe you ſee. It would be a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous wound vnto me all my life long if the dignitie of a cauſe worthy to haue the ſhoulders of al the princes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the coape of heauen for it footſtoole ſhould be anie whit diminiſhed by my foule hands, which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I proteſt to haue been waſhed as fair as their ſtains would permit. But I am not a little comforted, two maner of waies. Firſt that the Lord knoweth he thruſt me almoſt againſt my wil hereunto. And for aſmuch as I ſee the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Ieſus Chriſt (in whoſe countenance God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath louingly wincked at my ſinnes, and whoſe is al that I haue) ſtandeth vpon the progreſſe of the woorde preached among vs, my ſilence, though to the daunger of my life, ſhal not be tray his honour. Is not he a God? Will he not be religiouſly worſhipped? Wil he not haue this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion framed according vnto his owne mind? Hath hee not regard whether his true ſeruice be yeelded him or no? if he haue, woe be vnto that conſcience that knoweth this and keepeth it ſecret, or is ſlacke in the promoting hereof. Seing it pleaſed him, who alſo ſeparated me from my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers womb to ſtur me vp hereunto, I doubt not but hee wil giue that ſucceſſe of my labours, that may be moſt to his glory. Surely by his aſſiſtaunce I neither can nor will be ſlacke. The dignity of the cauſe (I hope) wil be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: if not, importance muſt take no deniall in the matter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14779:3"/>of our God. My ſecond comfort is, that what effect ſoeuer ſhal enſue my paines, I ſeek not my owne but theirs whom it concerneth, namely my parents and brethren according to the fleſh. Whoſe ſtate is ſo miſerable at this daie, that I think it were verie great vndiſcreetnes for me to ſpare anie ſpeech that were likely to preuaile. Naie I would to God my life coulde winne them the preaching of the Goſpel. Our ſicknes is at the hart, it muſt not be dallied with, either preſent remedy or vndoubted perdition. And ſo will they iudge, who viewe our eſtate offered vnto her Maieſty and the Parliament. Which was not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed onely leaſt poſterities ſhould knowe ſuch diſhonour of God either at al to haue beene, or in <hi>28.</hi> yeares not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed vnder Queen Elizabeth our ſouerain. As for the aduerſaries who vnderſtand our eſtate too wel and reioice at our ſilence, I regard them not at al, for what haue we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe at this day, which flowed not out of the midſt of their inheritance, curſed Rome, that bottomles pit &amp; fornace of idolatry? I haue only therein touched our calamity, &amp; not touched a great part thereof. To come vnto you beloued of the church of engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, I know our cauſe ſhal come through many of your hands, I do with teares beſeech that it maie haue al the lawful fauor you find of your harts to affourd vnto Chriſt in his poor members. It may ſtand in ſome one to daſh the whole. Therefore in the name of God I require al of you, that you hinder not his honour, the ſaluation of periſhing ſouls, &amp; the good to the common wealth hereby inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. If you do otherwiſe, I praie God, ſo many ſouls, as periſh in miſerable Wales for want of preaching, be not required at your hands in the daie of iudgement. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued I promiſe al good things on your parts, and craue not only praiers, vnto the Lord for the ſpeedy erecting of our Ieruſalem; but all other helpes of ſpeech and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14779:4"/>of motioning the matter vnto her Maieſty &amp; the Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; ſhewing the danger, of denying the great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and neceſſitie of granting our petition. It is your dutie which cannot bee ſhaken off, as it appeareth by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Ebed-melech,<note place="margin">Ierem. 38.9.</note> Ieremie <hi>38.9.</hi> The like act done by the Princes and Elders of the Lande, Ieremie. <hi>26.16, 17.</hi> When the Princes hard Baruch read in their eares, the wordes of the booke containing al the curſes Iehouah had determined to bring vpon Iſrael and Iuda &amp;c. it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by the holy Ghoſt, that they were affraid both one and other, and ſaid vnto Baruch, we wil certifie the king of theſe woords, and did ſo. Wherein they perfourmed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that which euery one of you before the Lord is bound to doe. Gods people requireth this at your handes. The ſtate of the common wealth and her Maieſties (whom the Lord in mercie deliuer from all forraigne and dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical treaſons) crie vnto euerie one of you that can giue anie counſel,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iliad.</hi> 3. A counſellor muſt not ſleepe all night.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. You muſt not ſleepe al night, in this caſe, but intreat the Lord, her maieſty, and this honourable court, to raiſe the miniſterie of his word in Wales. This matter concerneth al verie nearlie. The way to procure to your ſelues fauour with the Lord, and credite with her Maieſtie, is to ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite our cauſe, and ſo you ſhal find it. The more earneſt you be herein, the more honor ſhal be vnto the Lord, and her Maieſtie wil be the more beholding vnto you. Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chad-nezzer an idolater bleſſed the Lorde, becauſe Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drak Meſhak and Abednago the ſeruants of the liuing God,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.9.</note> changing the kings decree, did yeeld their bodies, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than they would worſhip anie other God. If they had been as backewarde as were other Iewes in this caſe, howe had that notable decree to the honour of God beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgated? ver. <hi>29.</hi> Where had been their commendation?
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14779:4"/>No other waie conueyeth the true fauour of anie prince vnto the ſubiect.<note place="margin">Prou. 10.22.</note> Gods bleſſing which maketh rich and honourable is ioined hereunto. Though it were otherwiſe, yet this thing is laid vpon you, be not diſobedient. And likely it is to be otherwiſe. For (I am affraid) behold that which the Lord hath built, he wil deſtroie, that which he hath planted he will roote vp.<note place="margin">Ierem. 45.45</note> And doe you ſeeke for great things vnto your ſelues? Seeke them not. If in the daie of trouble you will be hidden, you muſt be Ieremies, you muſt be Hebedmeleches, you muſt be Barucks. In theſe three men the Lord ſhewed, that euen in this life, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth great difference betweene the zealous and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme profeſſors. Ieremy for his roundnes in his office was beaten and put in the ſtocks,<note place="margin">Ier. 35.15.16 Ier. 29.26.27.</note> Iere. <hi>35.15.16.</hi> iudged wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to die, Ier. <hi>29.26.27.</hi> accounted a rauer and one that made himſelfe a prophet, Ier. <hi>29.26.27,</hi> a man that ſought not the wealth of his people but the hurt, Iere. <hi>38.4.</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedmelech was a noble man, but ſome thing ouer zealous, and one that would not stick to tel the king himſelfe that he had yeelded vnto his noble men in a thing that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in all that they had doone to Ieremie the Prophet, Ier. <hi>38.5.9.</hi> Baruch was out of fauor both with prince and prieſt, Ier. <hi>36.19.26.</hi> becauſe he fauoured Ieremie. But when the land was made deſolate, and the wordes of poore Ieremie became true, who then went vnto the wal? Verily the king and his nobles, prieſts, and prophets. And Ieremy the true ſeruant of the Lord, muſt haue a whole ſenat of noble men ſent to take him out of priſon and to know his wil, Nebuzaradan, Nebuſhaſban, Raebſaris, Neregal,<note place="margin">Ier. 39.4.13.</note> &amp;c. the king of Babeles princes. Hebedmelech ſhould not bee giuen into the hands of the men whom he feared, but bee ſurely deliuered becauſe hee put his truſt in Iehouah.<note place="margin">Ierem. 45.45.</note> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch ſhould haue his life giuen him for a pray. Howeſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14779:5"/>it goeth therefore, your ſeruice in our cauſe ſhall bee recompenſed. They that know what it is to haue their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities forgiuen, and their ſinnes couered by the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and paſſions of Ieſus Christ will be wounded, to ſee others vnder the curſe. The Churches of God round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs goe to wrack in Fraunce, Belgia and a great part of high Duch, I would Scotland had continued in her firſt loue, and that the hands of the builders were ſtrengthned among you. Come what will come, stand you manfully in the faith, my fathers and brethren, and according to the counſel of Iude<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> renew the battle againe with your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual enimy,<note place="margin">Iud. 3.</note> and contend with earneſtnes. It maie pleaſe God though the liuelie branches be cut off, to quicken vs dead boughes, by the vertue of our head Ieſus Chriſt. I doubt not by the Lords goodnes, if the truth be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed among vs through continual preaching, but that al which profeſſe Godlines in Europe, ſhall hartilie thank the Lord for our zeal and courage therein. Our nation are ful of droſſe I graunt, as al the ſonnes of Adam are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and verie ſtonie harted. But the word of God is a fire for the droſſe and an hamber for the ſtone Ier. <hi>23.29.</hi> And the weapons whereby the man of God warreth, are not carnal, but mightie through God to caſt downe houldes, and to bring vnder euerie imagination that is againſt the knowledge of God. <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>10.5.</hi> when al things ſhall be meaſured vnto vs by the meaſure of the ſanctuarie (as all muſt bee or elſe the building proue ruinous) our God will be for a diadem of beutie vnto vs, and for a ſpirite of iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he wil giue vs his ſpirit to pleaſe him. I thought it needleſſe to put hir Maieſtie and the Parliament in mind that euerie thing amongſt vs muſt be ordered accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word it ſelfe. For otherwiſe both the word and the Miniſter ſhall want a great deale of the dignitie due
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14779:5"/>vnto both. Suffer the ſcepter of the word to rule, &amp; this will not be derogatorious vnto man, much leſſe vnto the word. It wil be hard to find a yoke fellowe for that, which can neither abide ſuperior nor brooke an equal. My bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren for the moſt part know not what preaching mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, much leſſe think the ſame neceſſarie to ſaluation. Though they graunt it needeful, they think it ſufficient to heare one ſermon once perhaps in al their life. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was is needfull for me to ſet downe the neceſſitie of preaching, and of continual preaching, that if they labor not for the ſame, their bloode maie be vppon their owne heads. For they cannot denie themſelues to be put in mind hereof. If there be anie other point of doctrine tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it tendeth alſo to this end. The diligence beloued which I hope your learned Biſhoppes, Doctors and other great Diuines men of famous report haue taken in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, cannot ſuffer you to be ignorant in theſe pointes. Therefore take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not as written vnto you. For the caſe it ſelfe you know what it is, euen that which the Lord of hoſt will haue moſt ſeriouſlie thought vpon, &amp; graunted without al naie. In reſpect wherof it commeth with Gods own letters patents, wherewith all eſtates in the worlde, naie all the Angels in heauen cannot diſpence. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dling of it by me a wretch, I proteſt my ſelf to haue labored according to the example of the Apoſtle, to ſpeak as I haue beene allowed of my God, ſeeking to win the fauour of none, much leſſe the diſliking of anie, leaſt mans vnequall diſpleaſure would bee contented with no leſſe ſatisfaction than the bloode of manie a thouſand ſoules. God forbid mans infirmities in mee ſhould bring this effect. Naie it muſt not. For be I the ſonne of Adam ten thouſand times, compaſſed with neuer ſo manie infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, neuer ſo baſe, vile, polluted, and defiled, yet the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14779:6"/>preaching of the word in Wals is Gods glorie, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt ſtand. And yet it maie be the Lord by this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication doth but trie the good wils of thoſe ſmall or great through whoſe hands it ſhal come, and neuer mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to haue anie ſuch thing performed: as being out of hand to make an end of al, and to come himſelfe to ſit in iudgement, where his word ſhal be ſurelie countenanced. The conſideration whereof ſhould make men enter deeply into their dealings herein. O why ſhould the curſe of any damned ſoule among vs purſue the withſtander of our ſaluation? To make an end, pray for vs breethren and now pray, and pray againe that our God would encline mercie vnto vs in the ſight of the Queene hir Counſell and all the Queenes mightie princes, and that builders may be raiſed among vs. So let it be our God, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14779:6"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE NECESSITY laid vpon ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to<note n="a" place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.8. Iſai. 53.11.</note> know aright, the eternal, his creator, &amp; redeemer, &amp; to ſeiue him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; which is doone of that people alone,<note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12. 2. Tim. 19.10. 1. Cor. 1.22.</note> amongſt whome, the light of the Goſpell doth ſhine, as is not obſcurely ſhewed, by the Lordes ſeuere puniſhment, vpon them that are either<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Iud. 4. &amp; 15.</note> irreligious, or negligently regard, &amp; deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately contemne the trueth, being offered vnto them: ſo doth it moſt liuely appeare, by the Lords free and vndeſerued<note n="d" place="margin">Ezek. 36.32 1. Cor. 4.7. Rom. 4.2. Iam. 1.17.</note> (yet rewarding bleſſings) vpon all ſuch, as in an holy obedience conforme themſelues according to his will. What flames of vnquenchable vengeance, careleſſe negligence of Gods ſeruice, &amp; the wilfull reiecting thereof, hath ſtirred in former times amongſt nations; and will, as long as the iuſt God iuſtly requiteth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his word, kindle for euer amongſt poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, I wiſh all men duely to conſider. The Lords anger, for the ſinnes of his owne people, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, was executed vpon them to the ful: euen becauſe, they hardened<note n="e" place="margin">Ierem. 19.</note> their neckes, and would not heare his worde. The<note n="f" place="margin">Iere. 22.5.7.</note> Lord ſware by himſelfe, that the Temple ſhould bee laide waſt, that he would prepare deſtroiers againſt it:<note n="g" place="margin">Ierem. 21.5.</note> hee himſelfe with a ſtretched-out hand, and with a mightie arme, would fight againſt them, euen in anger, and in wrath, and in great indignation. And
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14779:7"/>becauſe<note n="h" place="margin">Ierem. 26.2.</note> they would not heare him their Citie ſhould be a curſe vnto all the nations of the earth. The whole<note n="i" place="margin">Ierem. 24.9.</note> people ſhould be giuen for a terrible plague to all kingdomes, for a reproch, for a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, for a common talke, and for a curſe vnto all places whither he ſhould caſt them. Coniah<note n="k" place="margin">Ierem. 22.24</note> the King himſelfe ſhould not eſcape, no though hee were the ſignet of the Lords owne right hand, yet ſhould he be plucked thence. Theſe plagues with many others moſt heauy and wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>full, did the Lord denounce againſt them by the handes of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and perfourmed by the hand of Nebucad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar king of Babell: Becauſe<note n="l" place="margin">Ierem. 40.3.</note> they ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord &amp; obeied not his voice, therefore theſe things came vpon them as it is manifeſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy 40.3. Which are not ſo lightly to be ſet by of any, as though they belonged properly vnto that time, and people, eſpecially ſeeing the Lord iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note n="m" place="margin">1. Pet. 1.17</note> without reſpect of perſons; and ſeeing that nation, kingdome and people that ſinneth againſt the Lord; ſhalbe deſtroied, as it appeareth by the tenor of his iudgement executed vpon Tyrus, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niueh, Babel, and other Monarchies of the world. There is no exception of the<note n="n" place="margin">Deut. 7.26. &amp; 30.15.19.</note> bleſſing and curſe; life and death; but the bleſſing and the life ſhalbee to him that obeyeth, the curſe and death ſhal bee vpon the diſobedient ſoule. Neither was the groſſe Idolatry of this people the only cauſe of their ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine; but the Lord would haue them acknowledge<note n="a" place="margin">Ierem. 2.19.</note> that it was an euill, yea a bitter euil that his fear was not in them. This alſo did the Leuits<note n="b" place="margin">Nehem. 3.9.</note> after their returne, confeſſe to haue beene the cauſe of their baniſhment, euen that their King, Princes, &amp;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14779:7"/>Prieſtes did not diligently attend, diligently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend I ſay vpon the commaundements of Iehoua. And in that great day, all wicked men ſhall know, that the Lorde will ſurely render confuſion in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, not onely vnto wicked doers, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vnto them<note n="d" place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.8.</note> that know not God. Nothing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore but ſhame, indignation, and wrath,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 2.8.9.</note> tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and anguiſh of ſoule in this life, can bee expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for of thoſe people, whoſe tongues &amp; workes are againſt Iehoua, to prouoke the eies of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note n="f" place="margin">Iſai. 3, 8.</note> and after this life, a tormenting portion in that lake that burneth with fire &amp; brimſtone, which is the ſecond death. Of which ſort al they muſt needs be, which neuer heard of that, which is the<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 1, 15. 1. Co. 1.21.</note> power of God to ſaluation to as many as beleeue. On the contrary ſide the proſperous eſtate of that nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, language, and people, whoſe God is the Lorde Iehoua, what hart will not reioice to ſee? If you will knowe therefore the roote of the floriſhing eſtate of any kingdome, Dauid<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 44.15.</note> telleth you that it is, in hauing Iehoua to be your God. The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell vpon this foundation were thought to be ſuch a gorgious<note n="i" place="margin">Deut. 4.6.</note> building, that all other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſeemed to be but cottages, and wormes-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in reſpect of them. For in that they<note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 26.16.17, 18, 19.34.26.</note> had ſet vp Iehoua to be their God, and to walke in his waies; to keep his ordinances, lawes, and ſtatutes, and to harken vnto his voice, the Lord alſo had ſet them vp that day to be a precious people vnto himſelfe; &amp; to make them high aboue all nations in praiſe, in name and in glory. A large declaration of the priuiledge of ſuch a people is recorded Pſalm. 33. Behold the eies of Iehouah doe looke vpon them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14779:8"/>that feare him, and wait for his kindneſſe, that hee may deliuer them from death, and keepe them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue in the time of famine. And in the life to come Iohn ſaith of them in the Reuelation,<note place="margin">Reue. 7.16.17</note> that they ſhall not hunger any more, neither ſhal the ſunne light on them nor any heat, for the lambe that is in the middeſt of the throne ſhall gouern them, &amp; lead them to the liuely fountaines of water, and God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eies. Oh then what Chriſtian, yea ingenious, humane, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall heart will not be greeued to ſee any people in ſuch a forlorne caſe, as not only to be bereaued of thoſe vnſpeakable bleſſings of the Lord, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of al they ſhal be partakers that fear him, but alſo laid open vnto the weapons of his reuenging and conſuming anger in this worlde, and in that to come, to his eternall and neuer ending wrath? And who would not ſtrain himſelfe to the vtmoſt of his ability, and beyond all his might, to make knowen the caſe of ſuch a people, vnto thoſe who both can, and alſo would find a remedy therunto? For mine owne part, becauſe I ſee the ſpirituall miſerie wherein wee nowe liue in the Country of WALES, for want of the preaching of the Goſpel and the great plagues that are like vndoubtedly to fall vpon vs for the ſame; I cannot but be ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected toward theſe our calamities, as in reſpect of the Lords honor, the deſire of the ſaluation of my breethren, my loyall obedience vnto her Maieſty, and the diſcharge of my own conſcience, I doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies from the bottome of mine heart wiſh and pray for the redreſſe heereof, &amp; nowe by writing with all humility and ſubmiſſion in the feare of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14779:8"/>God, lay open our eſtate, firſt vnto the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of your excellent Maieſty my dread ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Queene Elizabeth, vnto whom only of all the potentates of the earth, I owe all obedience and ſeruice in the Lord Ieſus, and next vnto the viewe of your high court of Parliament, deſiring you vpon my knees in the name of the great God the creator and preſeruer of heauen and earth; whoſe honor is now in hand, that our petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be ſo throughly waied, as our neceſſity requireth. The ſumme whereof is; that it would pleaſe your Maieſty, &amp; this honorable aſſembly, in a zealous and a godly compasſion, to regard the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and wofull eſtate of vs your poore ſubiects, &amp; breethren, which liue at this day altogither with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowledge of<note n="a" place="margin">Iſai. 43.11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> a ſauing God, becauſe we haue not<note n="b" place="margin">2. Chro. 15.2</note> teaching Miniſters among vs, &amp; that ſome order may be taken by your Maieſty and the eſtate, whereby wee may bee freed from that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroieng groſſe darckeneſſe of ignorance, wherein we nowe are bewrapped to the woe of our ſoules for euer: And ſo by our true conuerſion vnto the Lorde, we may auoid euerlaſting death, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the fierceneſſe of the wrath &amp; indignation, which we ſee iuſtly to hang ouer vs in this life. The remedy of this our grieuous caſe, is only had (and no other way) by ſpeedie<note n="d" place="margin">Luk. 10.2. Matth 9.8.</note> prouiding vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs ſuch paſtors, as may feede vs with the food of life, the pure worde of God, and bring vs home vnto the only<note n="a" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.4. Heb. 13.20. Luk. 22.25. Mark. 10.</note> Lord of paſtors, &amp; ſheepeheards, the Lord Ieſus. This is the ſumme of al (my dread ſoueraigne) that I your baſe vaſſall haue embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened my ſelfe to offer vnto you, and this your
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14779:9"/>high court of Parliament; wherein I proteſt that in reſpect of my weakeneſſe al maner of waies; the baſeneſſe of my condition, I intreated the Lorde to ſend vnto you by the hand of him whom<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 4.13.</note> hee ſhould ſende, that is by one endued with ſuch giftes, and authority alſo, as whereby the ſuite might haue purchaſed ſome countenance, and ſo be found more auaileable, and plauſible. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that this mine endeuor might be a means to ſtirre vp ſome ſuch, and that the Lorde, is the Lord of countenance, credit, and fauour, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can adde vnto his own cauſe; the good liking of men either more, or leſſe, as ſeemeth beſt vnto him, which only guideth the harts of the children of men. And that he is then fullie ſeen for his own glories<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 4.2. Ezek. 36.32.</note> ſake to bring the worke to paſſe that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the ſaluation of any, when hee vſeth moſt abiect, and vnfit tooles, I doe not doubt if it be his good pleaſure, but that this ſupplication, though put vp by a ſinfull weake hand, ſhal haue all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment that the meſſage of the liuing God deſireth to haue. And although our eſtate beeing duly waied, doth with moſt patheticall, &amp; pierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cries, (that may moue againe the very flinty rockes) make intreaty for it ſelfe, and declare the vnanſwerable neceſſity either of hauing our peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions graunted, or of the torments of our ſoules in hel fire for euer, and our fatal ruine in this life: yet I thought it moſt needefull in this briefe treatiſe to ſet downe ſome of the reaſons whereupon our petition is grounded, that by the view of them, it may appeare how daungerous a thing it is in the ſight of God and man to deny our ſuite. And here
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14779:9"/>verilie the cauſe may be ſeene at the firſt ſight to be inuironed with a two-fould wall (as it were) of moſt iuſt, and apparant equity. Firſt in reſpect of the honour of God, whereat eſpecially it aimeth. Secondly in regard of man, whom it doth not a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle concerne. Whether therefore you do conſider the Lord himſelfe whom we diſdain, and contemn (for want of better inſtruction out of his woord) by our vngodlie liues, or her gracious Maieſtie and this honourable aſſembly, who are bound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde with an vncancelable band to ſee the eternall verity of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt taught vnto, &amp; obeied of al the inhabitants within the precincts of her Maieſties dominions; or my deere brethren and countri-men, whoſe ioiful and happy felicity is this way ſought for, you ſhall find the ſupplication to be full of dutifull endeuors to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the maintenance of Gods glory, the ſafe eſtate of this kingdome, &amp; our ſoueraign, (whom the Lord long preſerue ouer vs) &amp; hurting none, full of equity on all parts. Wee deſire to haue the knowledge of our God, and the Lawes of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (whoſe ſubiectes in name wee profeſſe our ſelues, and in deede ought to bee) made knowne and taught vnto vs. We deſire that the tyranny of Sathan, who<note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4. Epheſ. 6.2. &amp; 2.23.</note> exerciſeth a regencie in the hearts of all them (amongſt whom Gods trueth hath not beene taught) may be ouerthrown<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 1.16. Heb. 4.12. Ier. 23.29.</note> by the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full arme of God the worde preached,<note n="c" place="margin">Iam. 1.21.</note> who can ſaue our ſoules. Now therefore to you right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, worſhipful, and reuerend of this Parliament (with al humility be it ſpoker) in the audience of our God, in the preſence of Ieſus Chriſt, and in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14779:10"/>witneſſe of euery child of God, who ſhall read this litle treatiſe, we moſt earneſtly and vehemently as in the cauſe of Ieſus Chriſt, and in the cauſe of our ſoules, entreate and beſeech you, cry and cal vpon you to do your endeuors, that Sathan may no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger keep vs in bondage, which ought to be imploi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſeruice of our God, and that the Lorde Ieſus his throne may be eſtabliſhed in our hartes,<note n="d" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.19. &amp; 3.16.</note> as it ought to be in thoſe which are his members. What intereſt hath ſathan in vs, that wee ſhould be permitted to be at his beck, and leaue vndoone the duty we owe vnto our moſt beneficial &amp; louing God, euen by the law of creation? Why ſhould he preuaile more with you which continually ſeeketh your deſtruction &amp; ours, than Ieſus Chriſt, whoſe loue towardes vs was ſealed with the loſſe of his life, euen then, when we were his enimies? Wil you reward his vnconceiueable kindneſſe in ſuch ſort: as to ſuffer any that you can hinder, to be ſworne ſeruants of his profeſſed enimies? Sworn ſeruants I ſay, for whoſoeuer ſerueth not the Lorde Chriſt in<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 6.16. &amp; 7.5. 2. Pet. 2.20.</note> newneſſe of life, and holineſſe of conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hath taken the oth of a ſouldier to ſerue ſinne vnder Sathans banner. Why ſhould the ſonne of God be bereaued of the title that he hath in his people, &amp; conueiance thereof made vnto a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable crature? Conſider I pray you the weight of the cauſe in this one point: it is concerning no leſſe matter tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a kingodme, yea the kingdome of the God of al kings, Ieſus Chriſt: the contention is betweene the moſt glorious in heauen &amp; earth, and his own ſlaue, where the indignity of the vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ought to moue you. We are wearie of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14779:10"/>bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie bondage of the one, and deſire the eaſie yoke of the other. In the abſence as it were of our Lord and king, wee haue none to runne vnto for helpe, but you, whom he hath placed aboue vs. Pitie our condition, naie rather let it bee ſeene that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice to haue ſuch oportunitie to enlarge, and make conſpicuous the glorie of your redeemer, that it may bee a witneſſe vnto your ſoules when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you depart this life, that indeede you haue quited your ſelues like men in the places where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he hath enioined you, by defacing the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Sathan. You are nowe to declare vnto which of the two you would haue vs ſubiectes, who ſhal be king, Sathan or the Lord Chriſt: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether of the two can preuaile more with you Not that the diuel is able, or dareth withſtand his maker, or that the Lord needeth the helpe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ouerthrow his forces, as not being of power to rule, vnleſſe man ſet the crowne vpon his head: but becauſe hee hath taken this courſe in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of his Church here vpon earth, that vnleſſe the Magiſtrate doe vphold his honour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sathan, it will fall to the ground for ought men can ſee, and hee hauing commaunded men of authority to be zealous in his cauſe, wil reward them according vnto their loue towardes him in this point. For hereby hee doth trie their good wils, in that he declareth his honour to be vſually meaſured in the hart of the people, according vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the proportion of the magiſtrates loue towards him: reſeruing alwaies vnto him neuertheleſſe the power to beget his loue in the ſubiectes, whoſe prince may be an Idolater: and to bridle the furie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14779:11"/>of his enemies when hee will, without the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of man; and to reedifie his Church, though al the kings vnder heauen gaineſaie the ſame. But this not proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them wil be to their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condemnation, becauſe they choſe rather to haue their people in the ſlauery of Sathan, than in the liberty of Chriſt. For one of them will, yea muſt needes beare rule in the hearts of all men; either the Lord by his ſpirit conueyed vnto them through the miniſtery of his word: or the old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, by his diueliſh illuſions. That both cannot rule togither,<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 12.25.29.</note> it is apparant, becauſe they are ſo contrarie the one to the other: the ſubiectes of both kingdomes diſagree, the lawes be diuerſe. If you chuſe the ſonne of God, and place him in his throne among vs, by the preaching of his Goſpell (for otherwiſe you cannot be ſaid to make choiſe of him) then aſſure your ſelues that the Lord will<note n="b" place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30</note> honour you, becauſe you honour him, and not forget the vpholding of his kingdome by you, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in ſuch an age: as wherein moſt of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates in the earth haue bereaued him of his right, and giuen their crowns vnto the beaſt. Then happy be your names and memories, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories of your poſterities for euer. And happy be the daies that euer we were borne to be gouerned by ſuch a godly Prince, and godly counſellers. But if you make worſe than Claucus his chaunge, and as much as in you lieth robbe Chriſt Ieſus of his kingly dignity, what are you to looke for at his handes, but the cruel deſtruction that is prepared for thoſe, who will not ſuffer the ſonne of God to rule ouer them, or theirs? Conſider, and conſider
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14779:11"/>againe, that they deny Ieſus Chriſt a kingdome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer theirs, and conſequently prefer Sathan before him; which deny the miniſtery of the Goſpell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people, vnder their gouernment. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of which aſſertion appeareth not onely by ſome places of Scripture before quoted: but alſo in that the woorde preached, is called the<note n="a" place="margin">Matt 13.19. Luke 8.11.</note> woord of the kingdome by our Sauiour himſelfe: and the glad tidings of the Goſpell called the<note n="b" place="margin">Luke 8.4. Matth. 3.1.</note> kingdome of heauen. By the parable of the vineyard which is ſaid to be the inheritance of the ſonne of God Matth. 21.38. and whereof he accounteth himſelfe robbed when he hath not fruit yeelded vnto him;<note place="margin">Matt. 21.38.</note> which only is done where the Goſpell floriſheth. In that the Ghoſpell is called the Ghoſpell of the<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 24 14.</note> kingdom. Wherein politik Gamaliel alſo<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 5.39.</note> geſſed aright that the High-prieſts and Sadduces ſhould be found to do nothing leſſe than <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, fight againſt God, if they withſtoode the courſe of the Goſpel. To be ſhort<note n="e" place="margin">verſe 31.</note> Peter in the very ſame chapter a little before maketh it a part of Chriſts prerogatiue roial, to work repentance in the hart of man, and aſſurance of remiſſion of ſins, which no Chriſtian wil ſaie to be otherwiſe effected, than by preaching. In ſo much as they muſt needes be conuinced to eneruate, and weaken the ſame ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignety of the Lord of life, who any way refuſe to haue them for whoſe wealth they are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide good lawes, inſtructed by the Goſpel. If this concluſion be true (as in very deed it is moſt true) oh how ought you of this honourable aſſemblie to labour, for the erecting of the miniſtery of the word in Wales, ſeeing they that wil be ſlack in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14779:12"/>ſame detract from the honour they owe vnto Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and plainly ſhewe how little they care whether his kingdome ſincketh or ſwimmeth. As for theſe that withſtand this, I dare boldly affirme them to conſpire with Sathan about the inuading of Chriſts kingdome, and moſt contumeliouſly to tread his crowne vnder foote. Where by the waie they are intreated with al reuerence to looke bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto their dealinges, who vnder the name of conformity, and obedience, ſtay the courſe of the miniſtery in any place, &amp; deſired to acknowledge this vnity to bee nothing elſe but a conſent with Satan to wreſt the ſcepter out of Chriſt his hand, and vndermine his chaire of eſtate; if they haue done heretofore fooliſhly, let them now, (follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the counſel of the wiſeman) lay their hands on their mouthes, and take heede leaſt by defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding former practiſes, they ad drunckennes vnto thirſt. It may be if men knew the ſinne of reſiſting the Goſpell to bee ſo hainous, they would perhaps further our ſuite; or at leaſt not hinder it. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the preaching of the woorde is thought no better than folly of worldly wiſemen, it commeth often to paſſe that the reiecting of a ſuite tending thereunto, is made a thing of ſmal moment. And although in very deed this ſinne be high treaſon againſt the Lord, yet the offenders herein will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch themſelues to ſeeke the honor of God, no leſſe than the earneſt furtherers of the woorde preached, yea though they throw al their blockiſh, and wilful reaſons in the way, to ſtop the paſſage of it. And leaſt men ſhoulde terme them by their rightname, they thinke the excuſe will ſtand in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14779:12"/>good ſteede, to ſaie, they cannot ſee how the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the Goſpell ſhould bee ſo odious in the ſight of God, and therefore no reaſon why they ſhould be thought kickers againſt the heauen, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they in euery point fauour the proceedings of their Prince. But how vaine and ridiculous is their excuſe? For ſhal a traitour be therefore acquited, becauſe he offending againſt the Lawes of God, and his ſoueraigne (as in transferring the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue due vnto his Prince vnto a forraine Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous ſhauen prieſt) proteſteth that he neither acknowledgeth not ſeeth his actions therein to bee traiterous? Or ſhall Pellagians, Papiſts, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, &amp;c. auoid the names and puniſhments of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes, becauſe they affirme nothing but that whereof, by the ſtrong deluſion of Sathan they are perſuaded? I trow not. No more can hee be ſaid to doe any thing leſſe than to iuſtle againſt the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and him that dwelleth therein, which put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his ſhoulder againſt the progreſſe of his woord, though his owne corruption will not ſuffer him to perceaue this his rauing madneſſe. As therefore you of this honourable aſſembly would not bee taken defacers of Gods glory: ſo in moſt humble wiſe I admoniſh you not to oppoſe your ſelues in any ſort againſt this our petition: and as you would find fauour at the handes of the iudge of al the woorld in the day of iudgement, and bee acquited before Ieſus Chriſt, and by him, further his honour to the vttermoſt of your power. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whoſe cauſe it is; what account hee maketh of it: how derogatorious it is vnto his glory, for you to deny vs the Goſpell. I know it will bee aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14779:13"/>here, that her Maieſty and the Parliament deny the true ſeruice of God vnto none, and haue taken order that no falſe religion ſhould bee vſed of anie ſubiect in this land. Which thing alſo I doe affirme from my hart, and thank God for, and the Lord wil not forget Queene Elizabeths kindneſſe in this thing towards his houſe. I adde moreouer, that if any the people of this Realme want the ſame in particular, which hee hath granted all in general, it is her wil they ſhould acquaint the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament with their cauſe, where they ought to bee heard Hitherto therefore tendeth my ſpeach. If we th. people of Wales making our eſtate known, ſhall not haue it redreſſed by this aſſembly, that then the ouerthrowe and weakning of Chriſtes kingdome is intended thorough this meanes (by them that ſhall binder preaching to be graunted vnto vs) our calling adding great ſtrength there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Let all know therefore how greatly it ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the honour of the moſt high God, (which he wil maintaine as the apple of his eie againſt al the euil willers thereof, vnto their vtter ruine and ſhamefull confuſion both of body and ſoule) that the lamp of the Goſpell ſhould bee ſet on fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs, and that a repulſe ſhould bee giuen to Ieſus Chriſt by repelling this our cauſe. Good my Lords, whoſe honour in the feare of God I deſire, thinke with your ſelues that the Lord of heauen, being now reiected of moſt nations of the earth is thruſt into this poore Iland of England, as into the furtheſt weſterne partes (ſauadge America, and that continent excepted) but ſurely his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment here, if one handmaid had not better
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14779:13"/>cheriſhed him, had beene very cold. He hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten threatned vs to depart, by taking her with him from ſuch vngrateful ſubiectes as wee are. Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular men he hath by his ſeueral bleſſing, and the ſound of his woord, from the higheſt to the loweſt ſollicited vnto his ſeruice. Alſer the moſt part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed. This one time he wil try whether the whole eſtate of the land will allowe him anie larger de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, than hitherto he enioied. And therefore he now knocketh by this our ſuite, at the doore of the Parliament, to know whether we the people of Wales ſhall bee graunted him, as his herytage. If it be denied, he proteſteth that hee will ſtay no longer. He expecteth an aunſwere: Haue a regard what ye doe. A greater matter cannot be conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon. What a ſhameful thing were it for man to deny his God, that which moſt concerneth his glory? Alas the day what hinderance wil it be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any of you to haue vs poore Welſhmen cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braters of the honour of our God? And what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure will it bee vnto you to haue him departed from this kingdome in a rage, becauſe he is not heard in that thing, wherein he moſt delighteth? And beleeue me, I am highly afraid he will take your denial ſo vnkindly, that England ſhal feele, by the taking away of his Goſpell, what a geſt it vngratefully loſt. Therefore, as I ſaid before, ſo I ſay againe, that our ſuit is not ſleightly to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto, much leſſe denied: becauſe vppon the graunting of it, not onely the ſaluation of many thouſand ſoules; but alſo the glory of the moſt mighty God relieth. It were extreme madneſſe for vs to be cold in that ſuite, wherein we woulde
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14779:14"/>haue others whom it concerneth not ſo much, to be vehement and earneſt. And we might iuſtly both before God, and men, fry againe in our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, if we were not moſt earneſt in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſuch weight. Saluation is not beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that care not whether they haue it or no: Nay our Sauiour ſetteth downe, that ſeeking for it will not ſerue, but there muſt be great ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vſed; and that with agony, and contention.<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Striue ſaith hee<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 13.24</note> to enter in at the ſtrait gate; for many I tel you wil<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſeeke to enter, and ſhal not be able. Maruel not therefore if we leaue no ſtone vnturned to come by that which is ſo precious, and ſo hardly found. But the obiection miniſtreth greater ſtrength to our argument. For either the Parliament muſt deale moſt iniuriouſly with her Maieſtie, and ſaie it is not her will to haue Chriſt Ieſus raigne ouer vs, (which far be it from ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring into anie mans heart) or that they will in a cauſe ſo directly tending vnto Gods glorie, and the good of the weale publicke, reſiſt that, which ſhe moſt of al would haue decreed. This later hath not beene found, and I hope neuer will be in the Parliament of England, as long as Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth hath the ſcepter in her hand. And can any man admire that we haue al this while of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties ragine been by the iuſt iudgement of God, without the word preached, and alſo read, as ſhall be ſhewed, whereas wee neuer as yet opened our mouthes for it? I am ſo far then, from conceiuing any vnduetifull thought of my ſoueraigne, and this high Court, as transferring the cauſe of our ignoraunce vpon them, that I proteſt in iuſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14779:14"/>on our ſelues. For when did that day ſhine this twenty eight yeares, and aboue, that anie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, (whom the Lorde had endued either with authority or giftes of learning) haue moued this cauſe effectually vnto her Maieſty, or the Court of Parliament? Though I would wiſh wee had found the fauour in their ſight, (howbeit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of our ſelues) to be driuen vnto the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adge of Ieſus Chriſt, againſt our wils, that ſome more might ſolemniſe the ſame, than doe at this day, to his honour and their owne eternall felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If any man will heere demaund, whether the Lorde requireth any more at the handes of this high Court in the cauſe of religion, than is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perfourmed, ſeeing there is not only permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on graunted, for al that will to profeſſe the truth; but alſo a commandement, that none aduenture the contrary, I anſwere he exacteth a great deale more. As to ſee that euery inferiour perſon, haue done his duety in the performance of that, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioined vnto him, for the planting of religion. To ſee, whether ſuch Lawes, as haue beene alreadie prouided, in that cauſe, haue beene put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, if not to conſider wher the fault was, and ſee it amended. To conſult whether a better order may be taken for the progreſſe of true religion, than hitherto hath been, and being found to put the ſame in execution. Againe, for as much, as the work is the ruling of Gods people, eſpeciallie to prouide, that the gouerment may be according to the Lords owne Lawes. Briefly where the word is not preached, there to eſtabliſh the ſame with ſpeed. Our whole country of Wales, as yet, being
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14779:15"/>altogether in ignorance, to endeuour themſelues in deed, to ſee the ſame called. In a word to order euery thing in euery particular parcell of this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and the other according vnto the Law, and teſtimony (for the declining there-from argueth great ouer-ſight and folly, as it is ſet downe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſai. 8.20. Otherwiſe the Lord ſhould enioine, more vnto a father, or maiſter in the gouernment of his family, than vnto a magiſtrate in the common wealth. For a father and ſo a maiſter, is not only bound to ſee, that his ſonne bee no Idolatour, or ſwearer (which would to God all fathers perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) but alſo to bring them vppe, in<note n="2" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.2.</note> inſtruction and information of the Lord. Did Abraham no more, think you, than command his ſeruants, that they ſhould take heede, they ſerued not the gods beyond the riuers, and wil them in ſome general ſort, to ſerue Iehouah? You ſhall find it otherwiſe recorded of him, Geneſis 17.19. Good Iehoſhuah proteſted that he, and his houſe, that is, all thoſe that were vnder his gouernment would ſerue Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah. In whoſe example the doubt will not bee worth the anſwere,<note place="margin">Iehoſh. 24.14</note> that Iehoſhuah doth content himſelfe in this place, onelie to haue barelie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the trueth vnto his people, and giuen them the choiſe whether they would profeſſe it or no, whereas his proteſtation importeth, that as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as would be gouerned by him, ſhould ſerue Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah. If they did otherwiſe, ſuch rebels againſt God, were not fit to bee his people. To omit, that the caſe is far vnlike, in the people of Wales, and the Iſraelites at this time, I would, that all, which be are the chiefe ſoueraigntie of anie common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14779:15"/>chriſtian (whether monarchie, Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie &amp;c.) would plainlie declare, that they ſhould not be their ſubiects, who would not be obedient vnto the Lord, as did Iehoſhuah in this place. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid tooke a band of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.7.</note> to keepe no ſuch in his houſe. Wherein it appeareth, that he did both denie the ſame, to be a cage for Idolatours, and in like maner would haue al things there accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the will of God. His care was no leſſe in the common wealth, as maie appeare by his great ſollicitude, in bringing home the<note n="a" place="margin">1 Chro. 13.5 1. Chro. 15.13</note> Ark, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing &amp; amending his careleſſe ouerſight here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in before committed, by his earneſt deſire to add as much dignitie as hee could vnto the ſeruice of God, in offering to build him an houſe.</p>
               <p>Laſtly the exhortation he made at his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, to the rulers, &amp; his ſonne Salomon proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth openly, what a care he had to ſee the Lorde honored of euery man in his kingdome. I thought good in this place to ſet downe Dauids wordes.<note n="b" place="margin">1. Chro 28.8.</note> Now therefore (ſaith he) in the ſight of al Iſrael, the congregation of Iehoua, &amp; in the eares of our God, keepe and make diligent enquiry, for all the commandements of Iehouah, your God, that you may poſſeſſe this land, and leaue it for an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance vnto your children after you, for euer. And thou Salomon my ſonne, knowe thou the God thy fathers, and worſhippe him with an vpright hart, and with a careful ſoule, for Iehouah ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hearts, and vnderſtandeth all the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the thoughts, if thou ſearch for him, he will be found of the; but if thou forſake him, he wil caſt thee off for euer. I ſee to whome I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14779:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpeake, and therefore application needeth not. Onely you are to marcke, that no ſeruice by picce-meale, but according vnto al the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes is allowable, and that the Magiſtrate muſt practiſe all that God requireth of him. The wil of God in any particular point of religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnknowen vnto him, hee muſt make diligent ſearch and inquiry for it himſelfe (keepe &amp; ſeeke all the commaundementes ſaith he.) In which wordes the holy ghoſt noteth, that a good magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may be ignorant of his duty, but giuing this caueat withall, that as ſoone as he is put in mind thereof,<note place="margin">We muſt ſeek vntil we find, and hauing ſound, keepe the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</note> though by an inferior perſon, he muſt not be borne in hande by any other that all is well (for how can that be well and in good caſe, which is not according to the Lordes wil?) but ſee refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation out of hand. The neceſſity of obaieng, is ſet downe, in that the Lord would not ſpare Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if he did the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, no, though he had made a promiſe of fauor vnto him. Further concerning the magiſtrates dutie in this particular care, that God be honoured through his charge, wee ſhall find in the example of good Iehoſaphat, who, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in the third yeare of his raigne, moſt<note n="a" place="margin">2. Chro. 17.9 2. Chro. 19.5.</note> nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly eſtabliſhed religion. (ſending Leuits about throughout all the Cities of Iudah to teach ithe people) notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, in the 18. or 17 year con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer 2. Chr. 16.5. 1. Kings 22.41. with the 1. Kin. 16.29. went through the people from Berſheba to mount Ephraim, and brought them againe vnto Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah the God of their fathers, ſo litle a thing was it in his eies, to haue once verie notablie refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his people, vnleſſe he did the ſame, as often
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14779:16"/>as need required. Religious Ioſhia,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 33.29.</note> caried the like heart with him. The good king rent his clothes, his heart melted within him with weeping, and wringing of handes, he humbled himſelfe before his God, and immediatly ſet vpon the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euery thing amiſſe, as ſoone as he perceiued the Lord to be diſhonored by neglecting the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of his will, in any point. But what nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he to haue taken all theſe paines? He had a promiſe, all ſhould go well in his daies, and after him, his people were ſure, to ſmart for their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſinnes. He had doone well for his part, falſ-religion was expelled in the 1. yeare of his raigne (this being the 18.) Iudah &amp; Ieruſalem were pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from their high places, time would not ſerue to eſtabliſh euery thing, according vnto the lawe of Moſes, the people were ſimple, not capeable of the gouernment, required by the worde of God, his nobility, by reaſon of their long continuance in Idolatry, not ſo well perſwaded of the true reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, he ſought to eſtabliſh. It was very new vnto them, their weakenes were to be born-withal: Yea they muſt haue the liberty of their conſciences. Perhaps they who ſhould haue beene moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as the high prieſt, and others, were found very great enimies, vnto all good proceedings. It may bee they looked, that all ſhould bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto their handes, as the pope hath done in times paſt. For what had a ciuil magiſtrate to doe with ſetting in order things belonging vnto religion? Theſe and many other hinderances, hee had I grant.<note place="margin">2. Chro. 34.3.</note> But looke when the zeal of the Lords houſe hath eaten vp any, how eaſily they ſwallow
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14779:17"/>all occaſions, that might hinder the true worſhip of God, in any that belongeth vnto them. And therfore, that very yeare, euen then, when he was farther inſtructed, by examining the booke of the Lawe of Moſes, concerning his duty, he gathered the people from the greateſt,<note place="margin">verſ. 30, 31, 32</note> to the ſmalleſt, prieſt and Leuite, read the woord, of the couenant in their eares, and made a couenant before Iehouah to keepe his commaundements, his ſtatutes, and his teſtimonies, with all his heart, and with all his ſoule. He cauſe al, that were found in Ieruſalem, and Beniamin, to ſtand vnto it. So farre was hee from bearing with any in their Idolatrous perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that could not (for conſciences ſake for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth) but turne backe from Iehouah the God of their fathers, that as it is recorded of him hee<note n="a" place="margin">verſe 33.</note> compelled all that were found in Iſrael, to agree vnto the couenant, &amp; to ſerue Iehouah their God which they did al his life. In which actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (religion being now receiued by publicke conſent) hee did not only according to the commandement<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 13.69.</note> &amp; the example of his pre deceſſors the<note n="b" place="margin">Iuſ. 22.21.19</note> whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>grega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the booke of Ioſhua and godly king Aſah<note n="c" place="margin">Chro. 15.13</note> (who de creed that whoſouer would not ſerue Iehouah, ſhould be ſtoned, whether he were ſmall or great) but alſo, that which the wonderfull, and great woorkes of God, wreſted from<note n="e" place="margin">Dan. 3.29.</note> Neubuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzer, and almoſt nature it ſelfe ſhewed vnto king Artaſhaſh.<note n="f" place="margin">Ezra. 7. a6.</note> Gods honorbeing precious in the eies of this aſſembly, as I hope it is, wil driue them to follow theſe godly examples, and to looke with the eies of an Egle, into the eſtate of our Church in Wales, yea compel vs, by authority rather than
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14779:17"/>faile to honour &amp; ſanctifie the Lord, by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſaluation. For then, he is ſaid to gaine a name, and maieſty to himſelfe, when he is ſeene, to forgiue ſins, not for mans deſert, but for his own<note n="g" place="margin">Iſai. 4.8.9.12</note> glory ſake: and he is then knowen to be the Lord, when hee is<note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 76.23</note> ſanctified in his people. For indeede none is able, either to forgiue ſinnes or to ſanctify the prophane hart of man, but the Lord himſelfe. Therefore the prerogatiue aboue all others giuen to out ſauior chriſt in the reuelation, is, that when there was none found in heauen or earth, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth, worthy to looke vpon the book ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſeauen ſeals, muchleſſe able to open it, he the lyon of the tribe of Iudah performed both.</p>
               <p>But who knoweth this ſaue they,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.13</note> that are redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by his blood? And his blood cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeth none, but theſe<hi rend="sup">i</hi> which heard the worde of trueth, euen the goſpel of ſaluation preached vnto them. The way then to procure, that the people of Wales maie cry with a loude voice, Woorthie is the lambe, to take the booke, &amp; open the ſeales thereof,<note place="margin">Reuel. 5.12</note> becauſe he was killed, and hath redeemed vs to God out of euery kindred, and tongues, people, and nation, is to beſtow the worde preached vpon them. And howe greatlie the calling of men vnto ſaluation augmenteth both the might, and the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding riches of Gods ſtrength, ſhalbe eaſily gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if you doe but conſider that the treaſury, the iewell houſe, and wardrobe (as I may ſay) of Gods glorious in heritance, in the Saints, and the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding greatnes of his power towardes them, that beleeue, is no other way diſcerned, but by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of reuelation, through the knowledge of god;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14779:18"/>as the expreſſe woords of the Apoſtle do enforce, Epheſ. 1.18.19. All which proceed from hearing the worde of truth,<note place="margin">verſe. 13</note> as he ſet down before. The wordes which the Apoſtle vſeth to expreſſe the meaning of the holy-ghoſt doth moſt euidentlie conuince that they who felt not this power in themſelues, count the Lord to be but a weakeling. For although the contemplation of nature,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>&amp;c.</note> the mouing of the heauens, and the creatures therein contained, may afforde ſome glimſe of the might that is in the creator; yet this is not indeede ſo much as a ſhadowe of the other, wherein the Lord is ſaid to exerciſe the power of his own right hand. As firſt in giuing the Lord Ieſus a conqueſt ouer al the<note n="k" place="margin">Coloſſ. 15</note> principalities, and powers of his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, making him to triumph ouer them, and that<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 2.10 18.4, 5. &amp; 5.7</note> by weakeneſſe, ſufferings, croſſes, calamities, temptations, yea and death it ſelfe: then in raiſing him from death, to giue him a name, aboue all names, and to make him the head of al. Secondly in vs, his poore members ſauing our helpleſſe, and damned ſoules, woorking mightily in our ſinful &amp; ſtony hearts, by the conuerſion of vs vnto him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> giuing vs poore fleſh and blood, a conqueſt alſo ouer our owne fleſhe, and the rebellious motions thereof: and which is more, ouer the prince of the world himſelfe. Aſſuring our vnbeleeuing hartes, of his loue towardes vs, ſhewing how mightie his ſpirite was in the Lorde Ieſus; who had it powred vppon him, without meaſure, ſeeing wee that haue but a dramme thereof, and that in a body of ſinne, are not without ſome reioicing effects by the power of Gods mightie ſpirite. Herein and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14779:18"/>in ſuch actions the power of God, to a beleeuing heart, ſheweth it ſelfe, to be ten thowſand times greater, than in creating a thouſand worlds. Can the Parliament of England be deſirous to glorify their God, and not decree, that this power of his be manifeſted vnto vs, by deliuering euery of vs out of the tyranny of that mighty potentate, who is euen the God of this world? Our ſauior Chriſt, euen in reſpect of his manhood is ſo glorified of his father; that man cannot augment the ſame, yet the Apoſtle is plain, that his honor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in no other point, than that euerie tongue ſhould confeſſe<note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 2.11.</note> him to be the Lord, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God the father, And leaſt carnall men ſhould thinke, the Lord ſmally to eſteem the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hee gaineth, by theſe, that are called vnto the knowledge of his trueth, the regard he hath here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, is two maner of waies ſhewed. Firſt, in that hee, which was the ſubſtance, and eſſence of the Lords owne glorious Maieſty<note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 2.6.</note> equall with God,<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 2.3. I ſaie 44.26 1 Iohn 1. Rom, 9.5.</note> God himſelfe, made himſelfe of no reputation, taking vpon him the forme of a ſeruaunt, became vile, &amp; bale, as we read, Eſai the 52 14.15.3. Phil. 2.7.8. onely to the end hee might reſerue from hell, ſome of the loſt ſonnes of Adam, by whoſe ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he ſhould be glorified. Secondly for aſmuch, as the chiefe end of his comming to iudgement, 2 Theſſ. 1.9. in that great and glorious daie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſecrets of all hearts ſhal appeare, is to bee made glorious in his Saintes, and marueilous in them that beleeue. It is out of controuerſie, that on this daie the Lord will make the maieſtie of his ſonne Chriſt, ſo glorious, and of ſuch rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14779:19"/>as the verie Aungels themſelues ſhall wonder and be aſtonied thereat: and yet there be none others ſet downe, in whom he ſhal be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. but only thoſe that beleeue. Shal we ſay then, the training vp of ſuch is of ſmal acceptaunce in his ſight? God forbid. Shall we think, that their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate wil be any thing tolerable, who in this life, though they doe not further the Goſpel, yet will not hinder the ſame? No truly. For here be onely two eſtates of men ſpoken of, either thoſe, in whom Chriſt Ieſus ſhall bee glorified (in euery of whoſe harts, the Lord hath ſo wrought, by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that they deſire nothing more, than that he maie rule the ſoules of men by his woord) or the other whoſe portion ſhall bee woe of ſoule. And who are they? only turks, infidels, papiſts, traitors, adulterers, theeues, murderers, and ſuch like wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquity? Theſe I graunt indeed, but not theſe alone. For the Apoſtle giueth no ſuch mark vnto al, but he comprehendeth both the one, and the other, in this, that they obey not the Goſpell. Be a man therefore accounted neuer ſo ciuilly honeſt, talk he neuer ſo well of the Church, and the dignity of the Goſpel, be he in ſhewe neuer ſo good a ſubiect vnto his prince (for the diuell is not ſo vnwiſe, as he wil haue al his limmes, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt breakers of the commandements, but he will vſe ſome viſured oppugners of Gods glorie) yet if in any ſort, you can perceaue, that he vſeth any other behauiour towardes Gods trueth, than he ought to ſhew there, whereunto greateſt obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and duety is to be yeelded, take him by and by for one, whom Paul meaneth. Becauſe he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beieth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14779:19"/>not, but vndutifully handleth the goſpel. Slips I grant the children of God may haue, and that very foul ones: but few of them ſo fal, as they muſt needs haue that to accompany them wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the honour of God is tied. We may ſee then what reckoning our ſauiour Chriſt maketh of the fruit he reapeth by the miniſters labour. And he wil maintaine his honour in this point, by the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine of al the clippers thereof, and be ſmally beholding (as wee heare) in heauen, vnto them that negligently labor for the ſame in earth. Here mark I beſeech you, that for as much as Sathan is permitted among vs, not only to lift vp his heel againſt his Lord, but euen to out-face him in his owne inheritance, the Lord threatned very lately and doth euerie day to meaſure our puniſhment, by the ſame line. Howe likely was it, had not he in mercy choked with their owne raiging ſpirits, theſe vnſatiable blood-ſuckers, Babington, and his adherentes, that we ſhould haue had in this kingdome the hand of the vile, againſt the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the baſe againſt the noble,<note place="margin">Iſaie 3.4.</note> the indigne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the woorthieſt of the land? Yea and the Lords anointed, the very<note n="a" place="margin">Lamen. 4, 20</note> breath of our noſtrils, ſhe vnder whoſe ſhadow we haue beene thus long preſerued from heathen popiſh tortors, was like to fall into their hands. The Lord graunt you of this honorable aſſembly wiſe harts before it be to late, to examine aright the cauſe of theſe vngodly attempts, &amp; to preuent the iſſues of them. Which ſhall neuer be done as long as the Parliament wil permitte Non-reſidences, impropriate liuinges, ſwarmes of vngodlie miniſters, the inſolent, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14779:20"/>tyrannicall proceedinges of ſome, ioined with pomp too too vnreaſonable, to keep out a learned and godlie miniſterie, by whoſe means the Lord Ieſus would recouer his owne againe. Perſuade your ſelues, that the Lord maie iuſtlie giue our poſſeſſions to ſtrangers, becauſe an enemie is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated in this land, quietly to enioie the right of Ieſus Chriſt, and by ſuffering ſuch vngodlie pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes countenanced in the action. If the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, French, or anie the forces of Rhomiſh Caine haue their deſire vpon vs (as I hope in God they neuer ſhall) how ſhall pluralities of impropriati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; other Church-liuings &amp;c. defend vs &amp; ours from their furie? To ſhut vp this point, all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer thinges confidered, is not our petition moſt reaſonable in regard of Gods honour? Wel in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of her Maieſtie, it hath manie reaſons where-vpon it maie be grounded. Can we euer hope to haue the tidings of ſaluation proclaimed in Wales, vnleſſe this be perfourmed in hir daies? And haue we a leaſe of hir life? Would it pleaſed God we had. Rather the door of our hope is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie day threatned to be ſhut. Now therefore the Lord warneth vs, to take the opportunity while it is offered. Now hee taketh heauen and earth to witnes that at this inſtant, at this Parliament, at this time of her Maieſties proſperous raigne, hee laieth before vs life and death good and euil, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and damnation, and that for euer. We ſhal neuer haue the time to chooſe againe for anie thing we knowe. And howe effectuall for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of her highnes think you would be the praiers of ſo manie thouſand of hir people, euen
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14779:20"/>of the whole welſh nation? Which ſhe now wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in aſmuch as they knowe not themſelues bound by reaſon of<note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2</note> the commandement, to pray for their Prince, becauſe the ſame was neuer taught them. When I conſider that an infinite number of vs truelie conuerted (in the feeling of ſuch a great benefit receaued at hir hands) would giue the Lorde no reſt daie or night, but ſtill bee begging of him to bleſſe our vertuous Queene E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth with the bleſſinges of a regenerat heart, and a proſperous quiet gouernment: when I call to mind, what an earneſt and ardent affection, a true Chriſtian beareth vnto his Prince (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly who beſtowed on him the meanes of ſaluation) and the promiſe of God, annexed to ſuch praiers, I cannot in duty but beſeech hir Maieſtie not to be wanting vnto hir owne ſafety euen in this one thing. Which ſhould not a little moue hir, ſeeing it was of ſuch great moment to ſtir vp<note n="b" place="margin">Ezra. 6.10</note> Cyrus to the ſpeedy erecting of gods honour at Ieruſalem. Moreouer you may be aſſured, dread ſoueraign, both that we and our children for euer wil bleſſe our God, that he hath enclined mercy vnto vs in your eies. And alſo our calling wil be a teſtimony of your burning zeale vnto the truth among all the ages to come, euen to the enemies of your good name. Whereas on the other ſide the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of our blind ignorance wil be I fear me a blemiſh vnto your credit (in obedience I ſpeak it) among our wofull poſterities, and the enemies of God for euer. For what will our children that riſe after vs and their children ſay, when they ſhal be brought vp in groſſe ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but that it was not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14779:21"/>Queene Elizabethes will, that we their Parentes ſhould haue that true religion ſhe profeſſed, made knowen vnto vs. Will not the enemies of Gods truth with vncleane mouthes auouch that ſhee had little regarde vnto true or falſe religion anie further than it belonged vnto hir profite? I would ſome of them did not ſlaunderouſly caſt abroade amongſt our people, that ſhe careth not whether the goſpel be preached or not preached. If ſhe did wee alſo ſhoulde bee moſt ſure to enioy it after twenty eight yeares and vpward of moſt proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous raigne. Theſe thinges derogating from her Maieſties honor in a moſt villanous ſort, muſt be withſtoode thorough hir ſelfe and this whole aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, by making prouiſion for vs betimes of the food of our ſoules. Becauſe I ſee this moſt notably detracteth from hir, I cannot in duety but repell and gainſay this ſlander, and with as loud a voice as ynck and paper can ſound, affirme and publiſh that ſhe would haue the truth made knowen vnto al her people, and wiſh al of them to be prophets. Which thing I truſt in God ſhall bee manifeſted vnto the woorld euen at this Parliament, wherein Wales ſhal be alotted vnto Ieſus Chriſt for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance. And good reaſon why it ſhould be ſo, becauſe thereupon ſtandeth the mainteinance of hir credit. Of al the men in the world therfore ſhe may be leaſt beholding to them that will not deal earneſtly in our behalfe. And we the inhabitantes of Wales may thinke that very ſtraunge that one ſuite, tending generally to the benefit of vs al, will not bee graunted vnto vs in twenty eight yeares, and that vnder hir Maieſtie, whoſe good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14779:21"/>vs is no Ieſſe we are aſſured then to the reſt of hir ſubiects. If wee doubted heereof, behold at this time, opportunity is offered to take away all ſuſpicion. Where-as the neglecting of our cauſe (beeing generall as it is) wil not bee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome occaſion of ielouſie, as though we were contemned &amp; not accounted of but as thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt baren corner of the land, ſo thought vnworthy to haue the ſeed of Gods woord ſowen amongſt vs, vnworthy to haue the ſeruice of the ſame God with hir Maieſty and the reſt hir ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects. You that are godly wiſe counſellers in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of eſtate, look whereunto the ſhutting out of our moſt humble petition may tend. For all the good faithful ſeruice that euer hir graund-father, father, brother, kings of eternal memory, hir ſiſter or hir ſelfe haue found at the hands of anie of our nation, we beſeech her this one reward, that we may enioy the woord of God, and leaue it for an inheritance vnto our children, with this memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al alſo, that it is Queen Elizabeths reward aſwel for the faithfulnes ſhe hir ſelf found in vs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we are already by hir proſperous Raigne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed, as alſo for the good wil our poore pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents haue declared to the loffe of their liues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her noble progenitors. This would neuer be forgotten, and I know it will be aunſwered againe with the forwardſt readines to yeeld dutifull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice vnto hir highnes that any prince could hope for at the hands of hir or his moſt louing ſubiects. It might greeue vs the leſſe to be denied the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, vnleſſe the ſame were the inheritance which our fore-fathers the Cymbrûbrittons many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14779:22"/>yeares agoe poſſeſſed in this lande. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though at this daie wee cannot cal true religion by the right name, yet are not our ſuperſtitious obſeruations the bloſſoms of that auncient truth our forefathers profeſſed and ſealed with their blood. But the impes of that lifeleſſe and brutiſh ſtock of Rome, planted in England by Auguſtine that proud friar, whoſe tyranical proceedings our diuines in Wales reſiſted euen to the loſſe of their liues. That theſe traſh be but of ſmall continuance among vs in reſpect of the antiquity the trueth hath had, I proue becauſe the vetie mother of them, the execrable Maſſe, was but yeſterday, as it were knowen vnto vs. Shewed by two reaſons. Firſt among the cartloades of oathes which wee haue, our people cannot tel for their liues how to ſweare by the maſſe. Secondly we haue the maſſe at the end of none of our holy daies. For Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe, Candlemaſſe &amp;c. wee name the day of the natiuity, the holy daie of Marie &amp;c. Which things doe prooue the Maſſe to haue had but colde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement among vs, but within this later age wherin ignorance and idolatrie by the iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God tooke ſuch deepe roote in England, that it can ouer our land alſo. The equitie then of our petition appeareth alſo in that we aske no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the poſſeſſion and inheritaunce of our fathers to be reſtored vnto vs, which they coulde not alienate from their children. This were a ſitte place to ſtir vp my deare countrimen to bee ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in obteining that iewell which is woorth all their riches beſides, beeing their owne right: but their forwardae, in other cauſes perſuadeth mee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14779:22"/>they wil not bee ſlacke in the matter of the ſoule. And why ſhould they not be earneſt? Doe they not ſee our daunger to be ſo maniſeſt that no wiſe man would ſpare either woords or life to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered there-from? Are they not aſſured they ſhall be heard? The reaſon amongſt many that might perſuade them of hir Maieſties readines to yeeld vnto their petition is this. Either it muſt be ſaid that her highnes would not haue the Lord hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with our ſaluation that hue in hir daies, and that ſhe enuieth vs that good, nay enuieth herſelf, yea reiecteth the infinite reward in the life to come, and aſſurance of ſafety, with diuerſe other benefits in this life freely offered vnto her, for adding vs vnto the kingdome of his ſon (which aſſertion I know they will deteſt and gaineſay:) or that ſhee greatly longing for the honour of God and our vnſpeakable good, deſirous of the crowne that ſhal bee giuen hir in the life to come, will be moſt carefull incontinently whatſoeuer may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, to plant the word in Wales. This later is to be embraced &amp; affirmed. Neither can it be ſaid that ſhe wil take leiſure herein, for that were plainly to ſay, her Maieſty waied not the honour of Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe many a thouſand of vs ſhould die before he were known to be a ſauiour of diſtreſſed ſoules. Shee hath otherwiſe learned Chriſt, and therefore knoweth that the Lorde muſt not ſtaie mans leaſure when hee woulde haue anie thing perfourmed towards his ſeruice. If one wil not do it, he can finde another whom he wil honor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h the deed. Shee hath learned that it is to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ken the Lordes omnipotencie and to teach him wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14779:23"/>and diſcretion to goe no farther in a matter required by him than mans reaſons ſeeth good likelie to come thereof. She aſſureth hir ſelfe the Lord is diſcreet &amp; wiſe inough in commanding, and therefore will doe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> will though hir king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhould be endaung<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red. For he ſufficiently recompenſeth the loſſe that befalleth to anie, while the execution of his will is attended vppon. This courſe ſhe tooke at hir firſt coronation. This courſe I doubt not ſhe wil take at this Parlament, euen this I ſaie: for who knoweth whether the Lord Ieſus meaneth to keepe his before we haue a ſecond proclaimed? Will you therefore good gentlemen (I ſpeake vnto you my fathers, my brethren, my kindred, and what name of loue elſe can be inuented, my deare countrimen) be mute where there is no queſtion you ſhal be hard, vnles the fault be in you? Indeed it concerneth vs poor inhabitants of Wales verie nearly to be hard, as wel in reſpect of our preſent miſery, as of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull calamity that is to fall vppon vs. Our caſe now is to bee eſpeciallie pittied in reſpect of the inner man. For howe many ſouls doe daily ſtarue and periſh among vs for want of knowledge? And how many are like ſtill to tread the ſame path? It grieueth me at the hart to conſider how hel is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged to receaue vs. And here the Lord knoweth and our ſoueraigne with this moſt honourable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly ſhal know that I doe not complaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our cauſe. For our eſtate is ſuch, that we haue not one in ſome ſcore of our pariſhes, that hath a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing knowledge. Thouſands there be of our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that know Ieſus Chriſt to be neither God nor
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14779:23"/>man, king, prieſt nor prophet: ô deſolate and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne conditiom! yea almoſt that neuer heard of him. If anie by the great goodneſſe of God be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, this came to paſſe not by the dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their paſtours which are either dumme or greedy dogs that delight in ſleeping, as ſaith the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (a few honeſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excepted) but either extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily through reading, or by meanes of their re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t and abode in ſome corner of the Church of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land where the goſpel is preached. And l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay it be preached there, to the glory of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of our ſoueraign, and the eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aſting good of that whole nobility, and people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſe kindnes towards ſtrangers, the Lord wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot forget. And our Godremember Queen Elizabeth herein, and wipe not out hir kindnes ſhewed toward thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhew mercy vnto hir, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that daie good Lorde, and forget hir not in this life alſo, ſeing by means of foſtering thy Goſpell in hir land, ſome of vs a people not regarded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> haue known the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſinnes, euen of our great ſinnes. Let this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be forgotten good Lord. I am caried I knowe not whither from my purpoſed intent. Theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort are ſome few gentlemen, or ſuch like. The reſt of our people are either ſuch as neuer think of anie religion true or falſe, plainly meere Atheiſts or ſtark blinded with ſuperſtition. The later are of 2 ſorts. The firſt crue is of obſtinate idolaters that would fain be again in execrable Rome, &amp; ſo hold for good diuinity whatſoeuer hath bin harched in that ſacrilegious neſt. But theſe may doe what they wil with vs: for nether ciuil magiſtrat nor Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop wil controul them. They may be, euen of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14779:24"/>Parliament houſe, leaſt that congregation ſhould be without ſome Acha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that might giue the Lord iuſt occaſion, to execrate his whole hoaſt. Hence flow our ſwarmes of ſouth ſaiers, and enchanters, ſuch as will not ſtick openly, to profeſſe that they walke, on Tueſdaies, and Thurſdaies at nights, with the fairies, of whom they brag themſelues to haue their knowlege. Theſe ſonnes of Belial, who ſhuld die the death, Leuit. 20.6. haue ſtroken ſuch an aſtoniſhing reuerence of the fairies, into the harts of our ſilly people, that they dare not name the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without honor. We cal them <hi>bendith û mamme,</hi> that is, ſuch as haue deſerued their mothers bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Now our people, wil neuer vtter, <hi>bendith û mamme,</hi> but they wil ſaie, <hi>bendith û mamme û dhûn,</hi> that is, their mothers bleſſing (which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the greateſt felicity that any creature can be capeable of) light vpon them, as though they were not to be named without reuerence. Hence proceed open defending of Purgatory &amp; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al preſence, praying vnto images &amp;c. with other infinit monſters.</p>
               <p>The other ſort is of good ſimple ſoules, that would full gladly learne the way vnto ſaluation, and ſpend their hart blood, for the ſafety of their godly Prince, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do claim more intereſt then the reſt of hir ſubiects whoſoeuer. And this is almoſt the only happines they haue. Theſe poore ſoules, becauſe the Idol paſtor can teach them nothing, entering more deeply with themſelues into the conſideration of things, find by the ſmall light of religion we enioy through the meanes of hir Maieſty, &amp; by the inſtinct of nature, that there
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14779:24"/>is a diuine eſſence who muſt be carefully and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly ſerued and praied vnto for al bleſſinges that would be obtained. Which things they ſee vnperfourmed publikely, therefore priuatly they aſſay what they can doe.</p>
               <p>But wofull eſtate, they being not taught out of the worde of God, what he is, that muſt be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; how he requireth this to be doone, inuent vnto themſelues, both their God, and the maner of his ſeruice: concerning ſaluation they either think, that the Lorde is bound to ſaue all men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are his creatures, or that al ſhal be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at the later day, at the intreaty of the virgin Mary, who ſhal deſire her ſonne, after iudgement giuen, to ſaue as many of the damned as may bee couered vnder her man till: this being graunted al the damned ſouls ſhalbe there ſhrouded and ſo ſaued from helſiar. This is the cauſe why our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple make but a mocke of ſinne. They thinke the ſoule only ſhal goe to heauen &amp; not the body alſo, whence it commeth that they ſay, they care nor what becommeth of their bodies, ſo their ſoules may bee ſaued. They aſcribe ſauadge cruelty vnto God the father, becauſe he puniſhed mans ſinne ſo ſeuerely, euen in his ſon Chriſt, the Lord Ieſus they commend. <hi>Nû wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th genûf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>him amy tady gwr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ûlon hinnû<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onûd cydymmaith da ûwr mab:</hi> I care not ſaith one for the father that cruel man, but the ſonne is a good fellowe. Durſt wee once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue theſe baſe cogitations of our Prince, I know it would not be tolerated. And I hope this religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and wiſe aſſembly will procure that the Lord may haue ſome more reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at our hands. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14779:25"/>the poor creatures can hear nothing at the mouth of their miniſter, how their ſinnes may be hidden &amp; their iniquities couered, it is a common ſaying euen among thoſe who care not for Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Antichriſt, that it was a good worlde then when a man might haue a pardon for his ſins in ſuch and ſuch a place for one 4 d. They ſee no feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city where mere ignorance of ſaluation is. A falſe perſwaſion thereof they thinke better than none at all. Man muſt haue religion true or falſe.</p>
               <p>Our people learn one of another moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous praiers. This they doe ſo much the rather, becauſe in them they comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d them ſelues, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, &amp;c. vnto the tuition of ſome ſaint whom they think moſt fauourable vnto them and beſt able to grant their petitions. My hart bleedeth to think howe theſe villanies with other vngodly ſongs are learned of good painfull ſoules with greedines. I know maſters of families that teach theſe vnto their houſholds. If they meete with any who can write and read, they wil demand of him whether he can teach them euer a good praier againſt ſuch a diſeaſe in man or beaſt. Vngodly welſh bookes are fraught with theſe Idolatries. If conſcience would not keep me from vttering an vntruth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my ſoueraigne monarch, yet fear of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould containe me. But this I proteſt before Ieſus Chriſt who ſhall iudge all euen according vnto their woordes, and in the preſence of al the world, that the onely ſtaffe &amp; ſtay of al priuat reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion among our people (the 2 ſorts of men before named I exempt, are latine praiers) praying vnto Saints, ſuperſtitious obſeruations, with vngodlie
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14779:25"/>welſh ſongs and books. If theſe things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, meate Atheiſme would ouer grow vs. Surely the reading miniſtery hath nor ſo much as wrought in the harts of anie almoſt, the perſuaſion of one true God. It were folly to goe about to heale the diſeaſe and let the cauſe remains. Concerning that which is reade, there is no man but thinketh very reuerently thereof. And we praiſe the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that we haue ſo much publikely by meanes of his highnes, whereas in the daies of blindnes we had nothing but profeſſed idolatry. Take but a view of our liues, and you ſhal ſee alſo what effect reading hath brought to paſſe. There be many ſinnes eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential almoſt vnto our nation. Profaning the name of God in common talk is prodigious, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> affirmations or negations will bring thirty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>hes out of a great many. Some ſhieres of South w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les haue gotten them an ignominious name by this ſin. I dare write that which I durſt not vtter in words. They are called <hi>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ûr eig Dû<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Looke the puniſhment of ſwearing Deut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Leuit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 15.16. This is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> book Zach. 13. Look the Law of concealing an oath Leu. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and you ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> finde that the Parliament ſhoulde haue great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to damme the ſpringes of this ſinne by the word preached. What a hand we haue had in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultery &amp; fornication, the great number of illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and baſe born among vs doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I would our Princes and Leuit, had not beans chiefe in this treſpaſſe. The puniſhment hereof in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops court is derided of our people. For what is it to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pay a litle money; or to run through the Church in a white ſheete? They haue made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:14779:26"/>and ſongs of this vulgar penance. Neither iuſtice of peace not miniſter wil ſee the execution of the lawes prouided in this caſe. Though they did, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lords ordinance is not obſerued, it would not preuaile. The ſeat of iudgement in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon courts is turned into wormwoode. A man cannot haue his right in a yeare or two, though his eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence be vnaunſwerable. They haue gotten ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhifts, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al failes one wil ſtand viz. excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication. The plaintife without al right maie be excommunicated in the Biſhops court, and ſo not abſolued in a whole yeare. Al which time hee is no perſon fit to proſecute his right in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law. It is irkſome to think how hardly a poor man can keepe any thing from the eues of great countenaunce. Though he ſeeth his own ſheep or other cattel feed within two miles of him in ſome mens paſtures, he dareth not aske them. Quaffing &amp; ſurfeting is too too common. Al are become Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maels. Euery mans hand againſt them, and theirs againſt all other. Church men and all will haue their right by the ſword, for by the word they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeek it. Theſe thinges I doe not ſet downe to diſgrace my deare countrimen. I beare them ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hart. My purpoſe is to ſhew that all the good politique lawes in the woorld cannot waſh awaie theſe our ſtains. The nitre that waſheth purely the word of the Lord muſt doe it. A conſcience muſt be wrought in our people, elſe they wil neuer leaue their idolatry, ſwearing, adulterie, and thee uery. They that know the country know how litle hold the ſtraighteſt and ſeue reſt laws in the world wil take on a great many. If it be the wil of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14779:26"/>therfore we ſhal be bettered, let the word be preached among vs. We haue preaching. How often? Quarterly. It is not ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For to that one pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh where there is one ordinary quarter ſermon, we haue twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty that haue none. The number of fit preaching miniſters in wales can eaſily proue the truth hereof. Wee paietithes alwaies, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould haue preaching alway, for he that laboureth not muſt not eat. 2. Theſſ. 3.8.10. conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall preaching is Gods ordinaunce. Eph. 4.12. therefore man muſt not diſpence with it. Confer Rom. 8.9. with Eph. 13.2. Tim. 4.2. Acts. 20.18.19.20.31. 1 Theſſ. 2.10.11. Heb. 5.12. Acts. 20.16. Coloſ. 3.16. 1. Pet. 1.23. Matt. 9.38. The ſeuerall reaſons drawen our of theſe places of Scripture maie proue the neceſſity of continual preaching, either in reſpect that it is Gods decree, or that mans nature requireth it. They that denſe this may learne their duty by Iacobs diligence in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of ſheep Gen. 31.40. So may they that ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to take the ouerſight of the Lordes ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie Ezec. 44.8. and bluſh. Preaching is graunted conuenient, but ſo as reading wil ſerue the turne. I maruel the face of mortall man wil be ſo braſen as to affirm this, the immortal word of god loudly gainſaying it, 1 Cor. 1 21. Rom. 1.16. Iam. 1.21. I wil not light a candle before the ſun. Though prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching be graunted neceſſary, and the word reade no meanes to ſaluation: yet there bee three diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties that inferre an impoſſibility to haue the ſame in Wales.</p>
               <p>The woorde in welſh neither muſt not can bee gotten. Muſt nor, becauſe al ſhould be brought to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14779:27"/>ſpeak Engliſh, of the condition the trueth were made knowen vnto them, I would it were brought to paſſe. And ſhal we be in ignorance vntil wee all learne Engliſh? This is not hir Maieſties will wee are aſſured. Raiſe vp preaching euen in welſh, &amp; the vniformity of the language wil bee ſooner attained. But why can we not haue preaching in our owne toung? Becauſe the miniſter is not able to vtter his mind in welſh. He maie. For wee haue as manie words as in any vulgar toung whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and we might borrow from the latine &amp;c. The ſtraunge words would become familiar thorough cuſtom. They that defend the contrary are ſlow bellies and not wel minded to doe their countrie any good. A good excuſe for the ſoul quelling non reſident. Admit we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not haue welſh preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, yet let vs not bee without Engliſh where it is vnderſtood. There is neuer a market towne in Wales where Engliſh is not as rife as welſh. From Cheapſtow to Weſtcheſter (the whole compaſſe of our land) on the Sea-ſide they all vnderſtand Engliſh. Where Munmoth &amp; Radnock ſhiers bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vppon the marches, they all ſpeake Engliſh. In Penbrok ſhier no great ſtore of Welſh. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider Angliſey, <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>û C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rnarûon,</hi> &amp; ſee if all theſe people muſt dwel vpon mount Gerizzin and be ſubiect to the curſe, becauſe they vnderſtand not the Engliſh toung. The ſecond difficulty is want of ſufficient number of miniſters. The aunſwere hereunto may be diuerſe. Firſt the harueſt is the Lords, therfore if he be ſought vnto, laborers ſhal be ſent Matt. 9.38. And extraordinary bleſſinges may be expected, if his ordinance ſhal take place
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14779:27"/>and mans remoued. Might it pleaſe hir Maieſtie and the Parliament to take this courſe, the Lorde would raiſe thoſe ſauiours Haba. 21. that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely in the fight of man. Further the a Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities are able to ſend out at this time three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred for the work of the miniſtery able me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery way with a little practiſe. Wee neede not haue all welſh preachers, therefore theſe alſo might ſerue our turnes, and it would be very hard if a doſen of them were not of our own people. Thus many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now prouided for, would be ſuch an incorage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto ſtudents, that at the yeares end twiſe as many would be ready to conſecrat themſelues to this holy labour. What an encouragement al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo would this be for men to ſend their Sonnes to the Vniuerſities, whereas they coulde no ſooner ſend them thither, than Colledges woulde haue places void for them? Now alas our Vniuerſities decay in number of ſtudents. They that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready placed, either dally with their ſtudies, or not apply them at all to diuinity, becauſe they ſee no end therof. Some bound by reaſon of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhips to enter into the miniſtery, wil make any ſhift to be diſpenced with, nay they wil giue euer their places rather than vndergoe this calling. The reaſons hereof bee two. Firſt the id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode hath made the moſt glorious function vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſun, moſt contemptible. Secondly they ſee the miniſter hath no aſſuraunce of that liuing whereunto he is inducted. Euery triſting matter it now made depriuation. If it ſhall pleaſe har high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and the Parliament to decree that euer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> godly learned miniſter may haue as good aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14779:28"/>of his ſiuing for terme of his own life, as any ſubiect in the land hath of his fee ſimple, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he be found ſuch an offender as his miniſtery wil be a reproch vnto the Goſpel, I doubt not but the miniſtery would be ſoone furniſhed with able me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. A number of the idle drones now in our mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie would become fit for that work in one year, if preaching were but here and there ſcattered among vs, and they weekely driuen to exerciſe. Where it may bee ſeene that their vndoing is not intended, but their good. There be many worthy men in the Church of England, that nowe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe not their publicke miniſtery, theſe would bee prouided for among vs. I hope they wil not bee vnwilling to come and gaine ſoules vnto Ieſus Chriſt. Priuate men that neuer were of Vniuerfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty haue well profited in diuinity. Theſe no doubt would proue more vpright in heart, as the Leuits in the like diſtreſſe 2. Chr. 29.34. then many of our learned men. For the preaching in Welſh, order might be taken that our breethren which are of the miniſtery in England ſhould be ſent home. Their flockes might be otherwiſe prouided for, &amp; they depart with conſent: Becauſe the neceſſitie of the Church requireth it.</p>
               <p>One of the 2. Vniuerſities ſince that ioyfull 17. day of Nouember 1557. haue ſent into the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, 3400. Graduats: all theſe number of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duats, a good courſe being taken, might haue bin found in the miniſtery of her maieſties own plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, &amp; not ſo few as 2. thouſand ouer-plus might haue bin imploied in other functions. Four-hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of theſe would haue beene ſince that time
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14779:28"/>wel placed in Wales, whereas at this day we haue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not 12. in all our country that doe diſcharge their duety in any good ſort. The proofe hereof I offer to ſtand vnto againſt all gain-ſaiers.</p>
               <p>I hope this wil be conſidered of. If not, wee may be eight and twenty years more without the word preached. The laſt difficulty is the want of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance for our miniſters. This is but a mere ſhift to bereaue the Lord of his honour, and vs of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Ezechia and Ioſia could alleadge the like, better than we can. The people of the Iews being in captiuity, had nothing of their owne to builde the Temple: yet becauſe they ſought the Lord in truth, hee ſturred vp Cyrus to prouide for them out of his owne reuenewes, Heſra. 6.8.9. So would he ſtir vp Queen Elizabeth, if we ſought him with an vpright hart. They whoſe harts the Lord hath touched, would threſh to get their liuing, rather than the people ſhould want preaching. Our gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and people, if they knew the good that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth preaching, would be ſoone brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute. They ſhould bee conſtrained thereunto. Saluation were not bought too dear with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fleſh of our armes.</p>
               <p>The honor we publickely yeeld in Wales vnto our god, the word preached being not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, if the lord be ſaid to alow of (which were blaſphemy to conceiue) he can be proued to be a meer Idoll. If to diſlike, where is that ſonne of Adam that wil preſume to offer him that which hee regardeth as the killing of a man, vntil he may be prouided for in a better ſort? Her Maieſty and this honourable aſſembly know that the ſeruice of the eternall is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14779:29"/>not to be diſperiſed withall, and therefore out of hand will ſee the erecting thereof, which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as long as any excuſe wil be admitted to hinder the worde preached. If impropriations &amp; Nonteſfidencies were not tolerated, a teaching miniſter in Walles might liue wel by the Church. Is it not intolerable that ſome of our Gentle-men ſhould haue 6. impropriate liuings?</p>
               <p>Our earneſt and humble petition vnto her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty and this high court of Parliament is, that it could pleaſe them to decree, that the tenth part of euery impropriat liuing in Wales, may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed to the maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of a teaching miniſter: which is ſo reaſonable, that I hope it wil be gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted And that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſter finding hir Maieſty ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſecurity, may be hir farmer in euery impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priat liuing, that belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vnto hir highnes within wales. We humbly intreat, that the ſame order may be taken with al improptiations in our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rey whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>Non-reſidencies haue cut the throte of out Church. Some that neuer preached haue three Church liuinges. Many of our liuinges are poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſtudents of either of the Vniuerſities: who neuer come amongſt vs, vnles it be to fleece. This I hope wil be tolerated no longer: ſeeing it is the very deſolation of the Church, the vndoing of the common wealth, and a demonſtratiue token, that the Lords will watch ouer vs to euill, and not to good: Our petition is that none whoſoeuer ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> poſſeſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one liuing, and that al may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to bee reſident on their charges. Theſe reaſonable petitions co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Non reſidencies
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14779:29"/>and impropriations being graunted, a great many liuinges will bee ready to entertaine a learned paſtor. Thus I hope al the difficulties that ſeemed to hinder preaching vnto vs are taken away.</p>
               <p>But I maruel what will be ſaid to bee the cauſe why we haue not had publicke reading in welſh to any purpoſe as yet. The old teſtament we haue not in our tongue, therefore the 1. leſſon is read in Engliſh vnto our people in many places that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not one word of it. This reading is taken to be the blaſphemous maſſe. And they giue it the very name of the maſſe. <hi>û maû yr offairiad ar y ffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> (ſay they, when the firſt leſſon is read,) that is the prieſt is at maſſe. One man ſeene in the original by the bleſſing of God would bee able to tranſlate the whole in 2. yeares: more handes would make more ſpeede. The ſmall prophets in welſh might he read vnto vs vntil we obtaine the whole, which ſhalbe ready for the Preſſe whenſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe hir Maieſty and the Parliament to call for them.</p>
               <p>Our humble petition is that the whole woorke may be ſet vpon incontinently, and that ſome or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may be taken for the charge of the impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The dialect that euery ſheire hath almoſt proper vnto it ſelfe, ſhould not hinder this woorke. For it preaching were in euery Pariſh, the people would be ſtirred vp to read the worde priuatly in their houſes, and ſo become acquainted with the phraſe. Our miniſters though neuer ſo ignorant, yet all vnderſtanding Engliſh, might eaſily reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy this, by conferring the Welſh with the Engliſh tranſlations, and ſo where they vnderſtood not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14779:30"/>their owneroung, the Engliſh might direct them, &amp; they their hearers. But they are far from taking this ſmall pains. I would ſome of them in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0. years had learned to reade welſh at the firſt ſight. They haue made the word of God of that baſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible account with many of our people, that they will aske to what end many thinges euen in the new teſtament it ſelfe are ſet downe. Becauſe they wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t preaching, ſome points of the high my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of ſaluation ſeeme vnto them to bee but vulgar and common, thinges not beſeeming the wiſedome of the great God. Bring ſome place out of Peter, Paul &amp;c. and their anſwere wil be, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth a wodhon ni pûneû bod hwûyn d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edûd gwir eû paidio?</hi> What know we whether they ſay tru or no? Is not this our caſe lamentable? The faculties and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of our Non reſidentes, whoſe abſence do imprint theſe skars of ſpiritual miſery vnto vs, wil not deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death. No they wil not ſhild vs from the temporal puniſhments that we now ſuſtaine (which is our ſecond miſery) for want of their dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. We feel the Lords ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d many waies againſt vs at this time in regard of the ſcarcity of all thinges, and eſpecially of victuals, and great number of poor. Euery man among vs was either wont to ſow as much corne as ſerued his familie al the year, or to make aſmuch of his ſheep and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cattle as might buy the ſame. The vnſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable harueſt 1585 yealded very little Corne. Therefore many were able to ſowe nothing the laſt year, becauſe they had not bread corne, much leſſe ſeed. The winter 1585 deſtroied al their cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wel near, ſo that now the very ſinowe of their
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14779:30"/>mainteinance is gone. Many that liued well and thriftily, are faine to giue ouer both houſe and home, and to go a begging. They were driuen the laſt harueſt to al the ſhifts in the world. As to rub the ſtanding come being not halfe ripe to make them ſome bread thereof. This famine is for our ſinnes, the Lord without our repentaunce faith it ſhal continue. Read Deut. 28.15.17.18. Amos. 4.8.11. It weer folly to continue in our ſin, for the lord wil make vs ſick againe in ſmiting of vs. Mich. 6.13 Leuit. 26.40. As long as the Lords houſe lieth waſt in our land, we ſhall ſow but meere ſalt.</p>
               <p>Haggai maketh this out of controuerſie. Reade the whole propheſie. Al the politicke Laws in the worlde, is not able to amend our eſtate vntill the Lordes houſe be builded, and thoſe ſent among vs who may teach vs by praier, and faſting, to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues before our God. This was the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of Ioel euen in the like caſe, and this wee muſt follow, or abide the ſmart of it. It were ſtrange that our eſtate being ſo many waies pitiful, would nor be redreſſed. You ſhall find it as yet more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, by entering into the conſideration of that which is like to fall vpon vs. Here firſt I wil not ſay, that the eſtate of that kingdome is verie ruinous, where there is not a preaching miniſter. 2. Chron. 15.2.5. God forbid that wee euer ſhould haue occaſion to ſay, that we haue no Prince,<note place="margin">Hoſea. 10.3. Ezra. 7.23.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we feare not Iehouah: as did thoſe wicked ones in Hoſhea his daies. Artaſhaſh was afraide that the Lord would be angry with the King, and his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: becauſe ſpeedy prouiſion was nor had for his true ſeruice in Ieruſalem. Confer: Prou. 14.18,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14779:31"/>with Hoſe. 7.13. and ſee whether the eſtate of that Prince whoſe people tranſgreſſe againſt God as wee do euen in pollicy is very daungerous. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiah was gathered to his fathers, becauſe he ſhould not ſee the miſery that was to fall vpon a more relligious people than we are. Think not the Lorde to winke al this while at our great ſins. Nay thinke rather that the Lorde will throwe as with a ſting the inhabitantes of our land, becauſe our paſtors are become beaſts &amp; haue not ſought Iehouah Ier. 10.18.21. There be two Archplagues (vndoubtedly to be expected for) of vs the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of Wales, if our petition be not graunted. The firſt indeed containing all the exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that may be inuented: yet leauing a place for the latter. In a woord it is the putting out of that ſmall light of religion which wee haue, the cutting off both of vs, and our poſterity from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto the Lord. The reaſon hereof is this: if the knights of our ſhiers and Biſhops &amp;c. will not ſhew themſelues deſirous to returne vnto the Lord with earneſt labour for the word preached, then they doe aſmuch as if they ſaid, the woord ſpoken vnto vs in the name of the Lord we will not heare, but we wil do whatſoeuer goeth out of our owne mouth, as did the wicked Iewes, Ier. 44. But what was replied vnto them? Verily this: Verſ. 26. Behold I haue ſworne by my great name ſaith Iehouah, that my name ſhal be no more cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon by the mouth of any man of Iuda in the land of Aegypt, ſaying Iehouah liueth. Our ſinnes being like vnto theirs ſhall be ſurely rewarded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. The other puniſhment is the vtter ruine of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14779:31"/>our land, the raſing of our names fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that we ſhal be no more a people. Ieremy maketh it but a ſmal matter with the Lord to ouer-throw a kingdome for the ſinnes of the people therein. Chap. 18.7.8.9. So doth Amos 9.8. We haue not indeed as yet a barren womb giuen vnto vs, but I feare me we haue brought forth children for the murtherers. Though we bring foorth children, yet will the Lorde ſlay the deareſt of our bodies: yea wo vnto them ſaith he when I depart from them. Hoſ. 9.21.17.</p>
               <p>Accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not theſe I pray you (whom I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore named) to be the viſions of the daies afarre off. Ezech. 12.18. but tremble and feare leaſt the Lord ſay the words in our daies and perform the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thinke rather the Lord to expoſtilate with vs: as he did ſometimes with the people of the Iewes. O you inhabitants of Wales, why wil you dy ſaith the Lord? Why ſhould I giue you for a terrible plague to al the kingdoms of the earth? Ier. 12.7. Why ſhould I forſake mine houſe, leaue mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, giue the dearely beloued of my ſoul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of her enimies? Ier. 3.12.13. &amp;c. Thou diſobedient (ſaith the Lord) return, and I wil not let my wrath fall vpon thee, for I am merciful. Be thou inſtructed leaſt my ſoule be diſmembred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, and I make thee a lande without an inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. Ier. 6.8. Think theſe ſpeeches I ſay to belong vnto you &amp; vs, &amp; in reſpect of them be vehement. The calamities of vs your kinſmé in the fleſh, yea your own and your childrens wil force you (or els you are vnnaturall) to vnfould our griefe vnto hir Maieſty and this aſſembly. Our caſe is pitiful you
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14779:32"/>know! Our life ſhort, we know not how ſoone the Lord wil cal for vs. How ſoon he wil make an end of al. If we haue not more knowledge than as yet we haue enioied meanes to come by the ſame, we can hope for nothing at his hand but that deadly voice, I know you not. You haue both<note n="a" place="margin">Herod. in Vra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> perſuaſion and neceſſity, which driue wiſe men, to take great matters in hand, to pricke you forwarde. Throw downe your ſelues before hir maieſty, and this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable aſſembly, and plead for your liues and your peoples: riſe not thence, vntill your ſuite bee yeelded vnto. We poore people look for nothing elſe but deſtruction, except our God graunt you fauour, at this verie inſtant time, in their ſight. I with in the Lord, that if wee periſh, we may periſh our ſelues alone: and that Queene Elizabeth and hir counſel with the eſtate, and the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munalty of England, may in a good conſcience teſtifie before the Lord, and ſay,<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 21.17.</note> Our hands haue not ſhed the blood of theſe men; neither haue our eies ſeene it. I do moſt earneſtly beſeech the Lord Iehouah (for his Chriſtes ſake) who is great and wiſe in counſell, ſeuere in puniſhing ſinne: yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant in mercy, and kindnes towards the bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and humble ſoule, to turne his wrath from vs, to giue hir Maieſty and this honourable court his ſpirit to direct them in euery action according vnto his word, to make al the enimies of his truth &amp; Queen Elizabeth like<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 29.22.</note> Ahab and Zedechiah whom the king of Babel burned in the fire, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue hir raigne ouer vs, haſten the comming of his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Amen.</hi> Amen. <hi>Yea come quiokelie Lord Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14779:32"/>
            <head>To the reader.</head>
            <p>Some rumor of the speedy diſſolution of the Parliament enforced me from the <hi>32</hi> Pag. or there abouts (ſo much being already vnder the preſſe) to cut off more of the booke by two parts than is now in the whole. The neerer I came to the ende, the more haſt I made. I regarded not herein —<hi>Amphora coepit</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inſtitui, currente rota cur vrceus exit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ouerſight I hope hath not been very great: if any, I hartilie craue pardon. How tedious &amp; vngainful it was for me to diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the whole and ſow togither the torne parts, let other men iudge. Some thing spoken of in the Epiſtle, could not be well perfourmed. Pag. <hi>30.</hi> l. <hi>22.</hi> Read, through-out his dominion.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
